A Guide to the Additional Papers of Alan Cheuse, 1983-1991
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Additional Papers of Alan Cheuse 1983-1991
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10726-i
This collection consists of ca. 1,220 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Alan Cheuse of Fairfax, Virginia, placed his papers on loan to the Library on July 19, 1991. The papers were purchased by the Library on September 11, 2003.
Scope and Content Information
This addition to the papers of novelist and book critic Alan Cheuse of George Mason University, Fairfax, Virginia, consists of ca. 1,220 items, 1983-1991, and undated, and contains manuscripts of the books, The Light Possessed and The Tennessee Waltz and Other Stories, and manuscripts of short stories and articles; book reviews; correspondence; printed material; family papers; a video cassette of a dance sequence; and typescripts of short stories and other material pertaining to the Sound of Writing programs for National Public Radio edited and directed by Alan Cheuse and Caroline Marshall, several of which were later included in an anthology.
The first series contains manuscripts by Alan Cheuse and is divided into two subseries consisting of A) the books The Light Possessed and The Tennessee Waltz and Other Stories, with a play adapted from Cheuse's novel, The Grandmother's Club and B) various short stories, articles, and book reviews.
The second series consists of professional and personal correspondence. Correspondents include: Nancy Ellen Abrams (1991 Jan 19); John W. Aldridge (1989 Nov 18); Rudolfo A. Anaya (1990 Jan 31); Ann Beattie (1990 Jan 26 and Feb 28 re opinion of The Light Possessed); Steve Becker (1990 Feb 13); Jane Bergmann (1990 Jan 10); Dulcy Brainard (1990 Feb 1 and Sep 16); Fred Busch,(1989 Nov 7); Lee Cullum (1989 Sep 18 and Dec 6; 1990 May 16, Sep 2, Nov 4 and Dec 26; and 1991 May 10); Digby Diehl (1990 Nov 14 and n.d.); Carl Djerassi (1990 Oct 2 and Nov 12); Stu Dybek (1990 Mar 22, Apr 5, and Sep 28); Richard Elman (1990 Jan 8 and 17, Feb 2 and 26, Mar 7 and Dec 5; and 1991 Apr 14); Richard Ford (1990 Dec 13; 1991 Jan 31); George Garrett (1989 Nov 21; 1990 Apr 9 and Sep 6; and 1991 Feb 23 and Mar 20); Herbert Gold (1990 Aug 29; and 1991 Apr 26); Jaimy Gordon (1990 May 5) Patricia Hampl (1990 Feb 28); Robert Hass (1990 Feb 10); Rust Hills (1989 Nov 15; 1990 Jan 24); James D. Houston (1989 Nov 3; 1990 Nov 15; and 1991 Feb 12, Mar 26, and Apr 24); Jeanne W. Houston (1989 Nov 1); Josephine Humphreys (1990 Feb 15; 1991 Mar 17); David Kaplan (1990 Feb 2, Mar 6 and Dec 6; 1991 May 10); Jim Kunstler (1990 Jan 15); Craig Lesley (1991 Jan 22); David Levin,(1990 Feb 15 and Mar 7); Mitch Markowitz (1990 Jan 10 and 22, Oct 19, and Dec 24); Terry McMillan (1990 Jan 23); James Michener (1990 Jan 9); Mary Morris (1990 Jan 9 and 25, Feb 5 and 20, and Oct 31; 1991 Mar 15); Carl Navarre (1989 Sep 18; 1990 Aug 2 and Sep 6; 1991 Mar 4 and Apr 11); Kent Nelson (1990 Jan 17 and Dec 11); John F. Nims (1991 May 3); Howard Norman (1990 Sep 15); Debra Nystrom (1990 Sep 18); Camille Paglia, (1990 Jan 2, Feb 6 and 26; 1991 Mar 29); Daniel J. Peters (1991 Jan 9); Robert Pinsky (1991 Mar 24 and Apr 17); Mark Richard (1989 Feb 15); Jim Salter (1990 Feb 1); Thomas Sanchez (n.d.); Neila Seshachari,(1989 Dec 10; 1990 Feb 15, Sep 6 and Nov 15); Robert Shapard (1989 Jan 2; 1990 Jan 26; and 1991 Feb 20 and May 13); Anna Shapiro (1990 Aug 17, Sep 12 and Nov 11; 1991 Feb 11); Barry Silesky (1989 Oct 15; 1991 Jan 8 and 12, and May 7); Lee Smith (1989 Aug 3); Wallace Stegner (1990 Mar 18 and Apr 9); Darcey Steinke (1989 Feb 22, Sep 22, Nov 9 and 24, and Dec 20; 1990 Feb 5, May 4, Aug 22 and 24, Sep 18, and Dec 24; and n.d.); Denise Thomas (1990 Feb 18, with short story "The Piano," Apr 10, Jul 23; and n.d.; Richard Tillinghast (1990 Oct 16; 1991 Apr 22); Jon Manchip White (1989 Dec 14; 1990 Aug 9; 1991 Jan 22; and n.d.); Allen Wier (1990 Feb 7, Nov 14; 1991 Mar 23); C.K. Williams (1991 May 6); Al Young (1990 Feb 6 and Apr 20); Grace Zabriskie (1990 Nov 26)
The third series consists of miscellaneous papers, printed material, photographs, reviews, an appointment calendar and manuscripts by other authors including George Garrett, Terry McMillan, and Robert Pinsky.
The Sound of Writing project aired on National Public Radio comprises the fourth series and contains material about the publication of a proposed anthology drawn from those stories read over the air, correspondence with authors seeking stories for the program, the scripts for the program, and the stories read over the air alphabetically arranged according to the author's last name.
Correspondents in The Sound of Writing Correspondence file include: Russell Banks (1991 Jan 19); Ann Beattie (1991 Mar 5); Ray Bradbury (1991 Mar 12); Robert Olen Butler (1989 Jan 1); Ron Carlson (1991 May 16); Josephine Carson (1988 Dec 27); Fred Chappell (1991 Mar 7); Joan Didion (1989 Sep 8); E.L. Doctorow (1991 Mar 20); Harriet Doerr (1989 Jul 22); Herbert Gold (EC) (1988 Dec 24); Allan Gurganus (1990 Aug); Gish Jen,(1991 Feb 13); Jim Kunstler (1988 Dec 22); Ursula Le Guin (1989 Jul 22); Lenny Michaels (1991 Feb 19, Mar 7); Mary Morris (1989 Sep 25); Mary Lee Settle (n.d.); Wallace Stegner (1989 Jul 26; 1991 Feb 2); Robert Sward (1991 Feb 5); Paul Theroux (1991 Mar 9)
Also present in this collection is an undated video cassette of a dance sequence entitled "Luminus."
Organization
Series I) Manuscripts by Alan Cheuse
Subseries A) Books and a Play (Boxes 1-3)
Subseries B) Short Stories, Articles, and Reviews (Box 3)
Series II) Correspondence (Boxes 4-5)
Series III) Manuscripts by Other Authors and Miscellaneous Papers (Box 6)
Series IV) The Sound of Writing Project (Boxes 7-9)
Contents List
- SERIES I: MANUSCRIPTS BY ALAN CHEUSE
  - SUBSERIES A: BOOKS and A PLAY
    - "The Grandmother's Club A Suite of Scenes" (Adapted from the Novel) by Alan Cheuse, w corrections by the author (2 folders) [ca. 1990 ?], TMs (Box 1)
    - "The Grandmother's Club A Suite of Scenes" (Adapted from the Novel) by Alan Cheuse [ca. 1990 ?], TMs (Box 1)
    - The Light Possessed by Alan Cheuse, with corrections (3 folders) [1989 ?], TMs (Box 1)
    - The Light Possessed by Alan Cheuse, Computer Printout (3 folders) [1990 ?], TMs (Box 2)
    - The Light Possessed by Alan Cheuse, with corrections 1990, Page Proofs (Box 2)
    - The Light Possessed by Alan Cheuse, Bound Uncorrected Page Proofs 1990, Page Proofs (Box 2)
    - The Light Possessed by Alan Cheuse 1990, Printed (EC) (Box 2)
    - The Light Possessed by Alan Cheuse, Miscellaneous Partial Drafts n.d., TMs (Box 2)
    - "Rose in the Skull" (published later as The Light Possessed) by Alan Cheuse - Miscellaneous Notes 1987-1988 (Box 2)
    - The Tennessee Waltz and Other Stories by Alan Cheuse, Bound Page Proof, autographed by the author 1990, Page Proofs (Box 3)
    - The Tennessee Waltz and Other Stories by Alan Cheuse, Bound Uncorrected Page Proofs, signed by author 1990, Page Proofs (Box 3)
  - SUBSERIES B: SHORT STORIES, ARTICLES, and REVIEWS
    - "American Literature in 1990" in The Britannica Yearbook by Alan Cheuse 1990, TMs (Box 3)
    - "Apache Woods" by Alan Cheuse, First Draft 1990 May, TMs (Box 3)
    - "Better Occasions" by Alan Cheuse n.d., TMs (Box 3)
    - "Bio" by Alan Cheuse n.d., 2 TMs (Box 3)
    - "Confessions of an Ex-Minimalist, or the Story in America Today" by Alan Cheuse [1990 ?], 3 TMs (Box 3)
    - "Dreamland" by Alan Cheuse in Weber Studies, First Draft 1990 Autumn, TMs (Box 3)
    - "Fast" by Alan Cheuse 1990, TMs (Box 3)
    - Georgia O'Keeffe articles by Alan Cheuse 1991 and n.d., 2 TMs (Box 3)
    - "How to Read Larry McMurtry" by Alan Cheuse 1988, 9 items (Box 3)
    - Introduction of Norman Mailer by Alan Cheuse at a George Mason University Bookstore Book Signing 1990 Apr, TMs (Box 3)
    - "James Salter" by Alan Cheuse n.d., TMs (Box 3)
    - "Land of Cotton" by Alan Cheuse n.d., Page Proofs (EC) (Box 3)
    - "Literature: United States" in The Britannica Yearbook by Alan Cheuse 1989, 15 items (Box 3)
    - "Little America" by Alan Cheuse n.d., TMs (Box 3)
    - "Nights on the Cumberland Plateau" by Alan Cheuse n.d., TMs (Box 3)
    - "A Note on Vidal's Messiah by Alan Cheuse 1991, TMs (Box 3)
    - "The Novelist as Critic" by Alan Cheuse n.d., TMs (Box 3)
    - "Objects in Mirror are Closer Than They Appear" by Alan Cheuse 1988, TMs (Box 3)
    - "Of Steinbeck and Salinas" by Alan Cheuse in The Boston Globe Magazine1984 Jan 29, Printed (EC) (Box 3)
    - "Old, Yes...Grand, Maybe" by Alan Cheuse in The Boston Globe Magazine1983 Dec 18, Printed (EC) (Box 3)
    - "The Pac-Man Murders" by Alan Cheuse n.d., 2 TMs (Box 3)
    - "The Quest for Ambrose Bierce" by Alan Cheuse n.d., Page Proofs (EC) (Box 3)
    - Reviews by Alan Cheuse 1988-1991, 59 items (Box 3)
    - "Reviews on Tape" by Alan Cheuse in Forbes FYI 1991, Printed (Box 3)
    - "The Rose and the Skull" by Alan Cheuse, and excerpt from The Light Possessed published in Story 1990, Page Proofs (EC) (Box 3)
    - "The Seals" by Alan Cheuse n.d., 2 TMs (Box 3)
    - "The Situation of Reviewing" by Alan Cheuse, with material pertaining to a symposium on reviewing including correspondence 1990-1991, 14 items (Box 3)
    - "Slides" by Alan Cheuse n.d., TMs (Box 3)
    - "Sources of Country Music" by Alan Cheuse n.d., TMs (Box 3)
    - "The Tennessee Waltz" by Alan Cheuse n.d., TMs (Box 3)
    - "Tripping the Lights Fantastic" by Alan Cheuse in The Boston Globe Magazine1983 May 29, Printed (EC) (Box 3)
    - "The Year in Letters, 1988" by Alan Cheuse [1988], 2 TMs (Box 3)
    - SERIES II: CORRESPONDENCE
    - Correspondence (7 folders) 1988-1990 Aug (Box 4)
    - Correspondence (7 folders) 1990 Sep-1991 May, n.d. (Box 5)
    - SERIES III: MANUSCRIPTS BY OTHER AUTHORS and MISCELLANEOUS PAPERS
    - Appointment Calendar 1989 (Box 6)
    - "Book Reviewing in America III and IV" and "The Year in the Short Story" by George Garrett, with a note by George Garrett to Alan Cheuse 1991 Feb 16 (Box 6)
    - Cheuse Family Papers 1987-1991, n.d. (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous Papers and Photographs 1989-1991, n.d. (Box 6)
    - Printed Material Concerning Alan Cheuse (2 folders) 1988-1991, n.d. (Box 6)
    - Reviews of Books written by Alan Cheuse 1989-1991 (Box 6)
    - "Waiting to Exhale" by Terry McMillan 1990 (Box 6)
    - Writing by Other Authors 1989-1991, n.d. (Box 6)
    - SERIES IV: THE SOUND OF WRITING PROJECT
    - The Sound of Writing Anthology 1989-1991, n.d. (Box 7)
    - The Sound of Writing Correspondence 1988-1991, n.d. (Box 7)
    - The Sound of Writing Scripts and Related Material (4 folders) ca. 1989-1991 (Box 7)
    - The Sound of Writing Stories: Authors A-H (7 folders) 1988-1991, n.d. (Box 8)
    - The Sound of Writing Stories: Authors K-Y (8 folders) 1990 and n.d. (Box 9)
- "Luminis" Dance Sequence (VC-32) n.d., VIDEO CASSETTE RECORDING (Box 9)